All right, בוקר טוב. Boker tov. So we pick up on ל״ו
עמוד א׳. Lamed vav amud aleph. We're at the two dots about
fifteen lines down. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda amar
Rav,
which is the line starts just the word לרב יהודה הלכתא כוותיה
דשמואל. l'Rav Yehuda hilchasa kevasei d'Shmuel. So we've been talking about this
צלף, tzlaf, this caper bush, and the issue has been that there
are various products that people harvest from the צלף tzlaf bush. And
the things that they are planted primarily for, you make בורא פרי
העץ. borei pri ha'etz. The things that are planted secondarily, or things
that can be also called the fruit, it's not just what they're
planted for, but the things that are considered the fruit are בורא
פרי העץ. borei pri ha'etz. The things that are not the fruit
or they're planted secondarily for are בורא פרי האדמה. borei pri ha'adama.
Okay?
That they are not the fruit or planted secondarily for are בורא
פרי האדמה. borei pri ha'adama. Right? That does raise a question exactly
how to identify fruit. Is it just what it's primarily for, or
it also seems like there's some objective reality to what a fruit
is. And as we're going to see now, the גמרא Gemara turns
to look at other areas where the definition of fruit matters. So
let's take a look. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב: Amar Rav Yehuda
amar Rav: צלף של ערלה, Tzlaf shel orla, let's say it's this
caper bush and it's ערלה, orla, the first three years. Now ערלה
orla is forbidden even outside of ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. And it
is, but it is rabbinic so it's more lenient. So let's take
a look. Or הלכה למשה מסיני, halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai, there's whatever. צלף
של ערלה, Tzlaf shel orla, so the צלף tzlaf of ערלה, orla,
בחוץ לארץ זורק את האביונות ואוכל את הקפריסין. b'chutz la'aretz zorek es
ha'avyonos v'ochel es ha'kafrisin. So if you want to benefit from the
צלף tzlaf tree, from the caper bush outside of outside of ארץ
ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, you throw out the אביונות, avyonos, which are the
fruit, because only the fruit of ערלה orla is forbidden, and you
can eat the קפריסין, kafrisin, which רש״י Rashi has been saying is
the shell of the fruit. שטיינזלץ Steinsaltz says it's the little buds
of the flower. So the גמרא Gemara says correct, that's what שטיינזלץ
Steinsaltz says. Okay.
No, no, I mean it is actually correct. I looked it up.
What? How do you...
what, that
קפריסין kafrisin is the... the אביונות? avyonos? Yeah.
Okay, whatever. All right. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: למימר
דאביונות פירא וקפריסין לאו פירא? L'meimar d'avyonos pira v'kafrisin lav pira? So
you mean to tell me that we're considering the אביונות avyonos a
fruit and the קפריסין, kafrisin, even if the shell or the buds,
not to be a fruit because the laws of ערלה orla don't
apply? ורמינהי, U'ramini, I'll ask you on this. Here's what we say:
המיני נצפה על עלים, Aminim nitzba al alim, so here's a ברייתא
braisa that we quoted before on the various aspects of the caper
bush, על עלים ועל תמרות, al alim v'al tmaros, on the leaves
and on the, רש״י Rashi would say it's like the little berries
or some other part of the leaves, אומר בורא פרי האדמה, omer
borei pri ha'adama, you say בורא פרי האדמה. borei pri ha'adama. ועל
אביונות ועל הקפריסין אומר בורא פרי העץ. V'al avyonos v'al ha'kafrisin omer
borei pri ha'etz. And on the fruit and on the קפריסין, kafrisin,
again we know what there's debate about that, you say בורא פרי
העץ. borei pri ha'etz. So now what's important about this question, and
it's always important to note this, is when the גמרא Gemara assumes
that categories are consistent across different הלכות. halachos. In secular law, you
would probably never assume this, right? You would assume that if you
had one law about importing fruits and vegetables, what constitutes a fruit,
what constitutes a vegetable, it wouldn't necessarily be the same as, I
don't know, some other law about the need to, you know, to
spray your fruits for bugs, who knows. You wouldn't assume that the
laws would be the same across categories that have very different concerns.
But in הלכה, halacha, very often we assume a universal application of
certain categories, although sometimes the גמרא Gemara will distinguish and it's an
interesting feature to note. So the גמרא Gemara says, look, if in
ערלה orla it's considered, you're distinguishing between the אביונות avyonos and the
קפריסין, kafrisin, one is a fruit and one isn't, how can you
say that by the ברכות brachos we make a בורא פרי העץ
borei pri ha'etz on both of them, assuming that the category of
fruit is the same in both areas? So the גמרא Gemara says,
let's see what the answer is: הוא דאמר כרבי עקיבא. Hu d'amar
k'Rabbi Akiva. Rather than challenging the ability to compare those two categories,
the גמרא Gemara says no, he's going according to the opinion of
רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. דתנן, D'tenan, it's taught in a משנה, Mishna,
by מעשרות. ma'asros. So now we're introducing yet a third category: ברכות,
brachos, ערלה, orla, and מעשר. ma'aser. What do we say by מעשר?
ma'aser? רבי אליעזר אומר צלף מתעשר תמרות אביונות וקפריסין. Rabbi Eliezer omer
tzlaf misa'er timrot avyonot v'kafrisin. So by the caper bush, you have
to take מעשר ma'aser on the תמרות, timrot, which רש״י Rashi says
are like berries, the אביונות avyonot are the fruit, and the קפריסין
kafrisin again is the shell or the buds, I don't know. רבי
עקיבא אומר אין מתעשר אלא אביונות בלבד. Rabbi Akiva omer ein misa'er
ela avyonot bilvad. No, only the אביונות. avyonot. מפני שהוא פירא, Mipnei
shehu pira, because that is a fruit. So it seems like they're
debating again what's considered a fruit. So fine, so when we say
you only make a ברכה bracha on the אביונות, avyonot, that is
רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. Other opinions would say there's a broader category
of fruit and again, assuming מעשר, ma'aser, ערלה, orla, and ברכות brachos
are all the same. So the גמרא Gemara says, ונימא הלכה כרבי
עקיבא? v'neima halacha k'Rabbi Akiva? Why not just say we rule like
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva in terms of this issue? Wait, I think
I might have misstated it. The אמר רב יהודה אמר רב Amar
Rav Yehuda amar Rav that says that by ערלה orla it's only
an issue, excuse me, of the אביונות, avyonot, is like רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva who says the same by מעשר. ma'aser. Our ברייתא braisa
by ברכות brachos includes the קפריסין, kafrisin, includes the shell, as a
fruit, but אמר רב יהודה אמר רב Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav
is going with רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva by מעשר, ma'aser, only the
actual fruit is the fruit. So the גמרא Gemara says, ונימא הלכה
כרבי עקיבא? v'neima halacha k'Rabbi Akiva? Why not just say we rule
like רבי עקיבא? Rabbi Akiva? And assumably if
we rule like him by
מעשר, ma'aser, we rule like him by
ברכות. brachos. So the גמרא Gemara says...
Maybe even in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael when it comes to ערלה
orlah issues, we limit ourselves just to the fruit itself. קא משמע
לן, kamashmalan, that's not why. We're lenient by what's considered the fruit
by ערלה orlah outside of Israel because כל המיקל בארץ, kol hameikel
b'aretz, if you're ever lenient about an ערלה orlah question in Israel,
הלכה כמותו בחוץ לארץ, halacha k'moso b'chutz l'aretz, we rule like that
outside of Israel. Since ערלה orlah outside of Israel is הלכה למשה
מסיני, halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai, it has greater leniencies associated with it, and
therefore we, if you take a lenient position when it comes to
ערלה orlah outside of Israel.
You'd say הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai is usually a greater
leniency?
No, here it is. Here, part of the tradition is that you're
מיקל meikel by ערלה. orlah. You take the more lenient position. Okay,
the גמרא Gemara says אבל בארץ לא. aval b'aretz lo. But in
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael we do not rule like this position. So
what are we saying now? We lined up three categories: ערלה, orlah,
מעשר, maaser, and ברכות. brachos. By ברכות brachos we say you make
a ברכה bracha not only on the fruit, but on the קפריסין,
kafrisin, the shell of the berries. By ערלה orlah we say the
position of רבי יהודה מר שמואל Rabbi Yehuda Mar Shmuel is only
the fruit. By מעשר maaser רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says only the
fruit, but the rabbis say a lot of things. Our problem by
מעשר, maaser, we're assuming all the categories are the same, and what
we're saying is by when it comes to
ערלה orlah we adopt the most lenient position, and we say only
the fruit. But when it comes to other things, maybe we'll adopt
a stricter position. We're not distinguishing between category, we're just distinguishing between
when we can be lenient and when not. So now the גמרא
Gemara says like
this, the תלמוד Talmud taking up the very problem that you had
raised, that is to say across categories they're not the same. We
don't apply...
No, it hasn't said that yet. All it has said is, yes
you're right, you can bring, you can support your position from ערלה
orlah based on the position of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva in מעשר.
maaser. Right. But we're not always going to adopt that position because
maybe it's only in cases where you're allowed to be lenient. But
saying that there are cases you're allowed to be lenient are not
saying that fundamentally the categories are different. Right.
Fundamentally the definition of fruit should be consistent. But the law can
be different.
Yes, the law can be different, but it's different to say it
can be different when there's a reason for leniency as opposed to
be saying it's different because fundamentally you can't compare the categories. I
see. Okay. So that's what the גמרא Gemara says. All right. So
anyway, so that's why we can rely on רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
by ערלה, orlah, but we wouldn't necessarily adopt that position elsewhere.
There was no biological science that could...
No, the way חז"ל Chazal categorize is not based on a particular
botanical... Well, Aristotle created categories for everything. Aristotle categorized. Yeah, I mean
they were starting to do those kinds of things back then. So
this but this is completely independent of that.
Yeah, I mean חז"ל Chazal never fully explicit how they defined the
categories and it's certainly not how we would scientifically categorize. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says, the גמרא Gemara says like this,
כמאן אזלא הא דתניא, k'man azla ha d'tanya, but בארץ לא. b'aretz
lo. ונימא הלכה כרבי עקיבא בחוץ לארץ. v'neima halacha k'Rabbi Akiva b'chutz
l'aretz. Why not just tell me, okay, we rule like רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva outside of Israel? דכל המיקל בארץ הלכה כמותו בחוץ לארץ.
d'kol hameikel b'aretz halacha k'moso b'chutz l'aretz. Because if you're lenient about
ערלה orlah in Israel, we'll be you know, if you take a
lenient position, we'll apply it, we'll rely on it outside of Israel
for ערלה orlah considerations. So גמרא Gemara says no. אי אמר הכי,
ei amar hachi, if you had said that, הוה אמינא, hava amina,
I would have thought, האי דגבי מעשר אילן, hai d'gabbei maaser ilan,
maybe we can only be lenient regarding something like מעשר maaser of
the trees, דבארץ גופא מדרבנן. d'b'aretz gufa m'drabbanan.
It's only rabbinic even in the land of Israel, because in Israel
מעשר maaser is only by... according to רש"י, Rashi, it's a question
about מעשר maaser by fruit... רש"י Rashi is quite clear that, excuse
me, that the מעשר maaser by fruit is rabbinic. So רש"י Rashi
says מעשר maaser is biblical only by grains and wine and oil.
So therefore... מדאורייתא. mid'oraisa.
Exactly, exactly. So there's a question with פירות peiros also with trees,
right? In other words...
Right. There's always a question about whether trees in Israel are biblical
here by various categories relating to agriculture. Here the גמרא Gemara is
clear that by מעשר maaser they're not. It's only as רש"י Rashi
says, it's only by the grains, wine, and oil. So I would
have said if you said we rule like רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
outside of Israel, maybe we rule like him
in
מעשר maaser outside of Israel, which is a double
דרבנן. derabbanan. מעשר maaser by fruit anyway is rabbinic in Israel, and
outside Israel it's even rabbinic again. So there we can rely on
him. אבל גבי ערלה, aval gabbei orlah, but when it comes to
ערלה, orlah, דבארץ מדאורייתא, d'b'aretz mid'oraisa, that it's biblical because ערלה orlah
is all about trees in the land of Israel, אימא בחוץ לארץ
נמי ניגזר, eima b'chutz l'aretz nami nigzar, maybe even outside of Israel
I will not be lenient like רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, קא משמע
לן kamashmalan that we are. But at the end of the day
what are we saying? ערלה, orlah, מעשר, maaser, and ברכות brachos all
have the same definition of fruit. The position that by ערלה orlah
you can limit fruit to just the fruit itself outside of Israel
is relying on one position by מעשר maaser because you can be
lenient by ערלה orlah outside of Israel. But fundamentally all these categories
have the same definition of fruit and according to the ברייתא braita
in ברכות brachos it doesn't only include the fruit itself, it also
includes the כפריסין kafrisin which are either the shell or the buds.
So now let's see where the גמרא gemara goes from this. רבינא
Ravina אשכחיה ashcheih למר בר רב אשי le-Mar bar Rav Ashi דקא
זריק אביונות ואכיל כפריסין. deka zarik evyonos ve-achil kafrisin.
He was doing this with his caper bush tree. He threw out
the אביונות, evyonos, the fruit themselves, and he ate the כפריסין kafrisin
because again this was this was ערלה orlah and it was outside
of Israel.
אמר ליה, Amar lei, do you eat the shell?
Again, רש"י Rashi says it's the shell.
שטיינזלץ Steinsaltz says it means little buds before the before the flower
opens which were eaten... it makes sense. אמר ליה, Amar lei, according
to רש"י Rashi he ate the shell, yeah. It's a type of
a shell you peeled off and that was somehow edible. Okay, so
אמר ליה amar lei he said to him, מאי דעתך? mai daatach?
כרבי עקיבא דמיקל? ke-Rebbi Akiva de-meikal?
You're going like רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva that's lenient? Again by מעשר
maaser therefore you're applying it here by
ערלה? orlah? וליעבד מר כבית שמאי? ve-le-aved mar ke-Beis Shammai? As long
as you're being lenient by ערלה orlah outside Israel, go as go
you know take it to an extreme, go like בית שמאי. Beis
Shammai. דמקילי טפי? de-mekili tefi? Even more lenient. Where do you see
that? דתנן. De-tenan. צלף. Tzelaf.
בית שמאי אומרים כלאים בכרם. Beis Shammai omrim kilayim be-kerem. Here's the
fourth category. כלאים, kilayim, okay, mixed seeds. Now you are allowed to
plant trees together with your vine. You cannot plant vegetables and other
things with your vine or grains with your vine, but you can
plant trees with your vine. So how do we define a caper
bush? So let's take a look. בית שמאי Beis Shammai says it
is כלאים kilayim in your vineyard and therefore you cannot consider it
like a tree. ובית הלל אומרים אין כלאים בכרם. u-Veis Hillel omrim
ein kilayim be-kerem. It's not it's more like a bush, it's not
a tree, it's more I'm sorry, the opposite. Yeah, בית שמאי Beis
Shammai I'm sorry... בית שמאי Beis Shammai says it is כלאים, kilayim,
it is not a tree, and בית הלל Beis Hillel says it's
not כלאים, kilayim, it is a tree. ואלו ואלו מודים שחייבין בערלה,
ve-elu ve-elu modim she-chayavin be-orlah, that you're obligated in ערלה. orlah. That
for ערלה orlah purposes it is a tree. So this by the
way משנה mishna makes it very clear, ברייתא braita really, makes it
very clear that the categories are different. We can debate what's a
tree by כלאים, kilayim, but when it comes to ערלה orlah we
all agree it's a tree. Okay, so right there it has that
fact that it's different based on categories. So but the גמרא gemara
doesn't is not happy. Let's take a look at the גמרא. gemara.
הגופא קשיא. Ha-gufa kashya. Wait a minute, this is internally contradictory. אמרת
צלף, Amart tzelaf, you said by a caper bush, בית שמאי אומרים
כלאים בכרם, Beis Shammai omrim kilayim be-kerem, makes כלאים kilayim in a
vineyard which means that it's not a tree. אלמא מין ירק הוא,
alma min yerek hu, it's a type of a vegetable. והדר תני
אלו ואלו מודים שחייבין בערלה. ve-hadar tani elu ve-elu modim she-chayavin be-orlah.
And then you say but they all agree that you're obligated in
ערלה. orlah. אלמא מין אילן הוא. alma min ilan hu. You see
that it's a tree. Now this is a great גמרא gemara because
the גמרא gemara is taking two different categories and basically assuming that
it has to be the same definition in both categories. So how
could בית שמאי Beis Shammai say it's not a tree for כלאים
kilayim and it is a tree for ערלה? orlah? So let's see
what the גמרא's gemara answer is. הא לא קשיא. Ha la kashya.
That's not difficult. בית שמאי ספוקי מספקא להו. Beis Shammai sepuki mesapka
lehu. They don't know how to categorize a caper bush tree. Is
it a bush? Is it a tree? Is it a vegetable? ועבדי
הכא לחומרא והכא לחומרא. ve-avdi hacha le-chumra ve-hacha le-chumra.
They take the lenient position both ways... again notice stringent, I'm sorry,
stringent. The גמרא gemara had multiple opportunities to distinguish between categories and
it consistently assumes that it's the same cross-category. So how come בית
שמאי Beis Shammai treats it as a tree by ערלה orlah and
not as a tree by כלאים? kilayim? Because he's strict both ways,
he doesn't know which category to put it in, so he'll be
strict by ערלה orlah and treat it like a tree. He'll be
strict by כלאים kilayim and treat it like a vegetable. It's one
or the other, he doesn't know, but so therefore he's going to
be strict both ways. So that's the בית שמאי Beis Shammai position.
So מכל מקום mi-kol makom לבית שמאי הוי ליה ספק ערלה, le-Beis
Shammai havei lei safek orlah, but okay at the end of the
day בית שמאי Beis Shammai says that this caper bush might not
be considered a tree at all, it might be considered a vegetable.
That's why he's strict by כלאים. kilayim. So since he considers the
possibility that this whole thing is not a tree... דתנן, de-tenan, ספק
ערלה בארץ ישראל אסור, safek orlah be-eretz yisrael assur, וסוריא מותר. u-ve-suria
muttar. If you have doubtful ערלה, orlah, in Israel it's forbidden, סוריא
Suria which is the lands near near Israel like lands that were
conquered by דוד, David, and they also conquered by חשמונאים, Chashmonaim, anyway
there we there we're stricter than other places. But nevertheless even once...
but by ערלה orlah when it's a doubt, even in סוריא Suria
it's permissible. ובחוצה לארץ, u-ve-chutz la-aretz, outside of סוריא, Suria, other lands
near Israel but even further that were never part of greater Israel.
Those... No, not בבל. Bavel. Well there's a question, whatever, but nearby
lands like even lower Jordan, whatever. Anyway, יורד ולוקח. yored ve-lokeiach. You
can even even if you know... Normally when you can be lenient
by a doubt you can't create the doubt. Okay, it's like "oh
my gosh it's a doubt I don't know what to do, okay
maybe in certain cases I can be lenient," but you can't intentionally
create the ספק. safek. But they were so lenient by ערלה orlah
outside of the land of Israel that they said that if you
know this guy has some ערלה orlah trees in his like... you
know, in his orchard and like you don't... You don't even know
which ones they are. Maybe he knows which ones they are. You
don't even know which- but you don't know which ones they are.
You can go and buy the stuff from him, you don't have
to ask, you can be lenient by ערלה, orlah, that lenient is
how you can be by ערלה orlah in חוץ לארץ. Chutz la-Aretz.
As long as those trees are not
orlah.
ובלבד שלא יראנו לוקט. u-vilvad she-lo yirenu loket. If you don't see
him picking, you might even know which trees are which. You know
those trees are ערלה, orlah, these aren't. You go down and they
have a, what's it called, a farmers market or fresh fruit right
by the stand. Fine, you know some of the trees are ערלה,
orlah, some aren't, as long as you don't see him picking straight
from the ערלה orlah trees and selling you those fruit, it's okay.
Okay? So you can sort of- you can actually be very lenient
by ערלה orlah in חוץ לארץ. Chutz la-Aretz. Now, רבי עקיבא- Rabbi
Akiva so now that's a question. We see how lenient we are
by ערלה orlah in חוץ לארץ, Chutz la-Aretz, right? So why not
rely on בית שמאי? Beit Shammai? בית שמאי Beit Shammai would say
that this caper bush, even the fruit might be considered a vegetable.
So, rely on the most lenient position and even eat the fruit
of the caper bush outside of ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So let's
see what the גמרא Gemara says one minute. רבי עקיבא במקום רבי
אליעזר עבדינן כותיה. Rabbi Akiva bimkom Rabbi Eliezer avdinan kevateih. When will
we be prepared to rely on a lenient position by ערלה? orlah?
If it's considered to be still a legitimate position. When there's a
רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, even though רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer disagrees, we'll
rule like רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, we'll rely on him even though
normally we don't rule like him. But בית שמאי במקום בית הלל
אינו משנה. Beit Shammai bimkom Beit Hillel eino mishnah. But בית שמאי
Beit Shammai once they're overruled by בית הלל, Beit Hillel, אינו משנה,
eino mishnah, no longer is considered, like, not a משנה, mishnah, it's
like no longer a legitimate position. This becomes an interesting question in
הלכה. Halacha. There's a general principle in הלכה, Halacha, not exactly the
same but what we're talking about here, but parallel, that you can
rely on a דעת יחיד בשעת הדחק. daat yachid bi-sh'at ha-dechak. That
when there's needed and there's a time that there's a great, you
know, great need, you can rely on a דעת יחיד, daat yachid,
on a minority opinion, even though that's not normally the הלכה. Halacha.
Now, there are questions, is it דאורייתא, de-Oraita, is it דרבנן, de-Rabbanan,
whatever, but anyway there are times that you can rely on a
minority opinion. So the question becomes, what constitutes a minority opinion? Anything
anybody ever once said in fifteen- in two thousand years? You know,
how much does it have to be at least recognized as a
legitimate minority opinion? So what the גמרא Gemara is saying here is
that once we've decided that we rule absolutely like בית הלל, Beit
Hillel, בית שמאי Beit Shammai stops even being a minority opinion, it's
off the table. So therefore, yes, we can rely- we can be
lenient by ערלה, orlah, we can rely on רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva,
but we're not going to rely on a position of בית שמאי
Beit Shammai that has been completely rejected. Yes.
No, I was going to say that, I was going to say
that, and well don't you- no I'm not going into it. But
my other question is, isn't there like a third thing?
I forget who it
was, isn't it unless you do חטי בשר חרצן ופג? chite basar
chartzan va-pag? Yeah, fine, but we're not- anyway. Right. Okay. So now
the
גמרא Gemara continues. ותפרקיה דנפקא שומר לפרי. ve-tiferkeih di-nafka shomer la-pri. One
minute, even within the ערלה orlah discussion itself, even if I admit
to you
that only the אביונות evyonot is a fruit and not this קפריסין,
kafrisin, either shell or berry. But even if it's not a fruit
per se, why isn't it ערלה? orlah? Because it is a protector
of the fruit. And we have a הלכה Halacha that a protector
of the fruit is also ערלה orlah like the fruit itself even
if it is not in itself defined as the fruit. Right. ורחמנא
אמר, ve-Rachmana amar, and the תורה Torah says, וערלתם ערלתו את פריו,
va-araltem aralto et piryo, you should create ערלה, orlah, you should sort
of make off-limits the fruit, and the את et is seen as
an extra word. את הטפל לפריו, et ha-tafel le-piryo, not just the
fruit, but the thing connected to the fruit, associated with the fruit.
עם, Im, and את et means עם, im,
with the fruit, thank you, with the fruit, the thing that comes
with the fruit. ומאי ניהו? U-mai nihu? What is it? שומר לפרי.
Shomer la-pri. The thing the- the thing that is a protector. Now,
this is why רש״י Rashi has all along been saying that קפריסין
kafrisin is some type of a shell, a shell maybe that's edible,
but not the fruit itself. Anyway because it's calling it a שומר.
shomer.
You know, שטיינזלץ Steinsaltz makes a very good argument that it's the
edible berry. I mean, even though that, you know, the term, whatever,
the Greek term that this word comes from and so on, never,
it doesn't explain in this גמרא Gemara what it means that it's
a שומר shomer to the fruit. So anyway, he left me a
little frustrated. But anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says, let it be
forbidden not as a fruit but as a protector of the fruit.
אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so says רבא, Rava, הכי אמר רבא, hachi
amar Rava, היכא דאיתא בין בתלוש בין במחובר. heicha de-ita bein bi-tlush
bein bi-mechubar. When do we say it becomes a protector of the
fruit? היכא דאיתא בין בתלוש בין במחובר. heicha de-ita bein bi-tlush bein
bi-mechubar.
When that שומר shomer is retained, that protector
exists even after you pluck it off. So for example, you could
imagine like a- a good example would be an orange rind. Okay,
it's not edible, it's not the fruit, but you pluck off the
orange and you still have the rind. So that would be a
protector that laws of ערלה orlah would apply. What? It is edible?
Well, you can't chew- I mean you can sort of- you do
like orange zest. It's normal people wouldn't directly eat orange peel. Okay,
anyway. All right, we get the idea. Banana peel, we get the
idea. All right, we get the idea, okay, walnut shells and so
on. There you could say. הכא במחובר איתא בתלוש hacha bi-mechubar ita
bi-tlush Here it's,
it doesn't exist when you pluck it off. What does that mean?
According to רש"י Rashi it means that somehow after it's plucked the
shell falls off. According to the Steinzaltz it doesn't even come off
with the fruit, it's stayed as a different thing. Anyway, so the
גמרא Gemara says איתיביה אביי, Eisvei Abaye, so אביי Abaye asked this.
פיטמא של רימון מצטרפת, Pitma she'rimon mitzterefet, if the the the פיטמא,
pitma, the crown of a pomegranate, here they've got this gorgeous picture,
I think they use that in their ads, right? This is the
one they use on their cover. That's a nice picture of a
pomegranate, there you go. Okay, so the פיטמא, pitma, which is the
hard sort of crown-like thing, right, that has like that star-like shape,
right, that
is part of the pomegranate. And that is considered part
of it. Now we're introducing a fifth halachic category, by which is
the idea of טומאה, tumah, and what's considered a connected and a
יד yad to or or a שומר shomer to the fruit, that
if you touch part of it, the rest becomes טמא. tamei. So
this פיטמא, pitma, this crown, is part is one unit with it.
It's also מצטרף mitztaref to give you a minimum size, a minimum
quantity. You need a minimum quantity in order for something to become
טמא. tamei.
Okay, so one minute, where were we? מצטרפת, mitzterefet, right, והנץ שלו
אינו מצטרף, ve'hanetz shelo eino mitztaref, but the נץ, netz, the bud
like or whatever is not, that is according that is like the
the stuff inside of the crown. The hairy stuff. The hairy stuff
that exists inside of that crown. If you look at those pictures
they have a nice, maybe that's, I don't know if that's same
thing or not. Anyway, okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says מדקאמר
הנץ שלו אינו מצטרף, mideka'amar hanetz shelo eino mitztaref, since you're saying
this fuzzy stuff is not considered one unit for the minimum size,
אלמא דלאו אוכלא הוא, alma delav ochla hu, so you're saying it's
not food. Okay, ותני גבי ערלה, ve'tani gabei orla, now now let's
go look, that's what we know from this law of טומאה, tumah,
that it's not food. Now let's go look at this law of
ערלה. orla. קליפי רימון, klipei rimon, the shell of a רימון, rimon,
that's a perfect example of a שומר, shomer, והנץ שלו, ve'hanetz shelo,
and the נץ, netz, קליפי אגוזים, klipei egozim, the shells of nuts,
והגרעינים, ve'hagarinim, and seeds, all these things חייבין בערלה. chayavin be'orla. So
seeds is not because they're שומר, shomer, just to understand that seeds
is considered a fruit. But anyway, but you see here that the
נץ netz is חייב בערלה. chayav be'orla. Now why is that an
issue? Because
the
נץ, netz, according presumably, the the question is is that this is
something that would also fall off after you pluck it. It would
not remain, maybe it would it would wither away and dry up
after you plucked it. So this נץ, netz, the גמרא Gemara says,
is a שומר shomer that does not exist after it's plucked, and
nevertheless it's חייב בערלה. chayav be'orla. So you see you cannot say
the difference is whether it continues to be exist after it's plucked.
So the גמרא Gemara says אלא אמר רבא, ela amar Rava, so
rather says רבא, Rava, היכי אמרינן דהוי שומר לפרי, heichi amrinan dehovei
shomer lapri, here's why you're right, you don't need it to exist
after it's plucked. Here's why the כפריסין kafrisin though is not a
שומר. shomer. When is it considered a protector for the fruit? היכא
דאיתיה בשעת גמר פירא, heicha de'iteih besha'at gmar peira, when it's there
when the fruit is finished ripening. הא כפריסין ליתיה בשעת גמר פירא.
ha kafrisin leiteih besha'at gmar peira. This כפריסין kafrisin is not around
when the fruit finishes ripening, presumably it falls off.
And how was and how was he throwing out the כפריסין? kafrisin?
Oh, maybe כפריסין, kafrisin,
yeah, that's a good question. That's a good question. I don't know.
So the גמרא Gemara says איני והאמר, eini ve'ha'amar, the גמרא Gemara
says, ואמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה, ve'amar Rav Nachman amar
Rabbah bar Avuha, הני מתחלי דערלה אסירי, hani mitchali de'orla asiri, הוו
ונעשו שומר לפרי, hovei vena'asu shomer lapri, these מתחלי mitchali of ערלה,
orla, which are we checked these dates of ערלה, orla, are forbidden,
and I'm sorry, these are like a a cover of the dates
or something associated near the dates that protect the dates. רש"י Rashi
says it does the same function as this כפריסין. kafrisin. So this
is some type of a protector of the dates of ערלה orla
are forbidden, הוו ונעשו שומר לפרי, hovei vena'asu shomer lapri, because they
protect the fruit. And the גמרא Gemara says ושומר לפרי אימת הוי,
v'shomer lapri eimat hovei, when do these מתחלי, mitchali, when do they
protect these
dates? בכופרא, bekuphra, when the date is still unripe. וקא קרי ליה
שומר לפרי, veka kari lei shomer lapri, and you see it's considered
a protector. So again, here we see that we see by ערלה
orla to be considered a protector, it does not have to be
around after the fruit is plucked. That's like the fuzzy stuff of
the pomegranate, it does not have to be around when the fruit
finishes ripening, that's like this this
מתחלי mitchali of dates. Again, I don't exactly know the botany to
describe it better to you, but anyway we see it does not
have to be around when it's ripening, when it's when it's finished
ripening, it does not have to be around after it's plucked. Anything
that's considered a protector of the fruit. So we're back to our
question, why are these כפריסין kafrisin not ערלה, orla, let them be
a protector of the fruit? So the גמרא Gemara says, רב נחמן
סבר לה כרבי יוסי, Rav Nachman savar lah k'Rabbi Yosi, now רב
נחמן Rav Nachman who says it's not a problem, he feels like
רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, דתנן, detnan, רבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yosi omer,
סמדר אסור מפני שהוא פרי, smadar assur mipnei shehu peri, ופליגי רבנן
עליה. upligi rabbanan aleih. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says that סמדר smadar
is is forbidden, which is unripe grapes, because it's considered a fruit
even when it's unripe. And the rabbis disagree with him. So basically
the גמרא Gemara says we're not giving up on our claim. Our
claim is it's only a שומר shomer if it's around when the
thing is considered a a full fruit, ripe. But when do you
consider a fruit? How ripe is ripe? How when at what stage
of development is it a fruit? So if you so this position
that
The thing for dates is a problem is because it's a position
that holds that things are considered a fruit even at an earlier
ripening stage and it holds that by grapes and it'll hold that
by dates and that's why it considers the protector of dates to
be a problem because this position holds that even by a date
it's considered already a fruit even at an early stage. But if
we hold that it's not a fruit till a later stage we're
still saying, insisting, that the protector be there when it fully becomes
a fruit.
So the idea is that the identity of something is not necessarily
is not necessarily inherent in it until a certain stage in its
maturity. In other words if something becomes something it's not that thing
prior to a certain stage.
Well the way I would explain this from a הלכה halakha standpoint
the way I would explain it is that the הלכה halakha is
it has to be a שומר את פריו. shomer et piryo. It
has to be a שומר shomer of the פרי. pri. So if
this thing is protecting the thing which is not yet a fruit,
the thing that is not yet considered, you know, it's growing, it's
blossoming, it's not a פרי pri then it isn't a שומר shomer
of the פרי. pri. It's a שומר shomer of the future פרי
pri but it's not a שומר shomer of the פרי. pri. Correct.
So only once, so what we are claiming is yes, it has
to be around when the thing is considered a פרי pri but
we can debate when that happens because when that is. Is it
a פרי pri even when it's unripe or is it only a
פרי pri when it's ripe?
So that's exactly, the בעיא baaya is it a שומר shomer now
knowing that it will have that function once the thing it's guarding
is in a certain maturity? Exactly. And that idea can apply to
a lot of different types of circumstances.
Right. Right. What stage something has about something that's in potential and
not yet actualized. Correct. Like a baby.
Exactly.
Exactly thinking about that. Okay, yes.
But
I still don't understand why we're having
this discussion.
We are on a bit of a tangent here. Okay. The discussion
is is that because by the caper bush, okay, we said you
make a ברכה beracha בורא פרי העץ borei pri haetz on the
fruit and on this thing called קפריסין kafrisin which is some type
of a protector of the fruit. And now we are asking from
all different areas of הלכה halakha how do we define fruit assuming
the definition is all the same and this case of the caper
bush is a fascinating way of you know that gets explored in
all these different areas. So we see in ערלה orlah there's an
opinion that says that only the fruit is considered the fruit and
not this קפריסין, kafrisin, not this protector. But the גמרא gemara is
now focusing on ערלה, orlah, got off the ברכה beracha topic, focusing
on ערלה orlah and saying even if the protector isn't a fruit
it should be ערלה orlah because it's a protector of the fruit.
And that is one of and that is forbidden for ערלה orlah
as well. So that's where we are, we're on that sort of
digression.
But
I
still don't understand the argumentation. If somebody can use something as a
fruit that's associated with the fruit why would you have to parse
it out about whether it is or it isn't?
Because can I go ahead, if the תורה Torah says I can't
derive benefit from my fruit for three years can I go ahead
and peel off the peel of my orange and use the orange
zest? Can I use the bark of my orange tree during the
first three years? Yes. Can I use the leaves? Yes. Can I
use the rind of the orange? Oh I don't know I have
to think about that. Okay so that's the question. How do you
define what is fruit because it's only the fruit of the tree
that's forbidden, not all parts of the tree. So is the peel
forbidden? Are things that protect the fruit? So we're saying now it
doesn't have to be fruit to be forbidden even a protector. But
now we're trying to define what's considered a protector. Let's say it
protects it before it becomes a fruit but it's not around when
it does become a fruit. So that's this sort of formal definition
of what is a protector. So the גמרא gemara is now saying
yes it has to be around when it's a fruit but there
could be debate what's considered a fruit how stage of ripening is
considered a fruit. So the גמרא gemara says ופליגי רבנן עליה upligi
rabanan alei and the rabbis would argue they say it only becomes
a fruit later and therefore it's only a protector later. So now
the גמרא gemara says מתיבלה רב שימי מנהרדעא mativla Rav Shimi mi-Nehardea
Rav Shimi from Nehardea asked ובשאר אילני מי פליגי רבנן עליה uvishar
ilanei mi pligi rabanan alei
one minute, that debate was about unripe grapes okay and whether unripe
grapes are considered a fruit or not but is it really true
they would agree by other by other fruits? דתנן datnan we have
a משנה mishna that says מאימתי אין קוצצים את האילנות בשביעית meimatai
ein kotzetzim et ha-ilanot bi-sheviit here's yet another category שמיטה shemita okay
so you cannot go ahead and harvest your fruit on שמיטה shemita
when is it considering to be that you're picking your fruit and
when is it considered to be that you're chopping down your tree?
Let's say your tree has fruit on it, is that considered harvesting
fruit or is that considered chopping down your tree? Just like we
learned in זרעים. zeraim. Right. Yeah so partly it has to do
with are there developed fruit on the tree yet or not? So
בית שמאי אומרים כל האילנות משיוציאו Beit Shammai omrim kol ha-ilanot misheyotziu
all the trees once the fruit basically you know comes out doesn't
have to ripen it just comes out. ובית הלל אומרים u-Beit Hillel
omrim and Beit Hillel says החרובין משישרשרו hacharuvim misheyisharsheru it's not just
when it comes out, carobs is when it like makes a type
of a chain I guess it's what it looks like when it
develops at a certain stage. והגפנים משיגרעו vehagefanim misheyigreu vines when they
become the size of like we're going to say like a bean.
והזיתים אלו משינצו vehazeitim elu misheyanetzu when they blossom. ושאר כל האילנות
veshaar kol hailanot and all other and all other fruit. I'm just
starting where it says משינצו misheyanitzu יראה yare'eh okay רש"י Rashi says
when they nate anyway it's fine anyway ושאר כל האילנות vishar kol
ha'ilanos משיצאו misheyotziu all other fruits I don't know all other I
thought it says something in all other free trees when the fruit
comes out okay ואמר רב אסי ve'amar Rav Assi הוא בוסר הוא
גרוע hu boser hu gerua גרוע gerua when Beis Shammai says that
vines are משיגריעו misheyagriu it
means בוסר boser בוסר boser is this unripe state of the grape
of the grape הוא פול הלבן hu pul halavan and that is
the size of this type of a white bean and so literally
it says it is a white bean so the גמרא Gemara says
פול הלבן סלקא דעתך pul halavan salka dachas a grape is a
white bean אלא אימא ela eima כשעור פול הלבן keshiur pul halavan
it's the size of a white bean fine so that's what you
get by שמיטה shmita now מאן שמעת ליה man shams lei דאמר
de'amar בוסר boser אין in סמדר smadar לא lo
who is the one that tells you that a grape is only
considered a fruit when it gets to the stage of בוסר boser
which is further than סמדר smadar סמדר smadar is the very highly
unripe בוסר boser is a little bit further who is the one
that says that it's only a grape at that stage רבנן rabbanan
it's the rabbis who argue on רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yosi says it's a grape even at the early סמדר smadar
stage and the rabbis say only at the בוסר boser stage it's
interesting right סמדר smadar is a woman's name never בוסר boser is
a woman's name anyway אבות אכלו בוסר
ושני בנים תקהינה
avos achlu
boser
veshinei vanim tikeina
anyway so for so the גמרא Gemara says ותני vesani שאר כל
האילנות משיצאו shar kol ha'ilanos misheyotziu
so fine by grapes it's when it's the בוסר boser stage but
all other it means a little bit more developed but all other
trees is when the fruit comes out even when it's unripe so
you see if by שמיטה shmita it's considered a fruit as soon
as it emerges logically it should be considered a fruit in other
categories even at a very early stage okay so you can so
now we're back to our question something it can be a is
is considered a fruit even if it's unripe and therefore if it's
true by שמיטה shmita it should be true by you know it
should be true by everything else by what else do we have
here if it's true by שמיטה shmita it should be true by
טומאה tuma it should be true by ערלה orla and therefore why
we're back to this question why are the כפריסין kafrisin not a
protector of the fruit you can't tell me the fruit is unripe
and that's why they're not a protector because even unripe should be
considered a fruit now before we get to the answer I do
want to point out because obviously this is a point I've been
making how the גמרא Gemara completely assumes identity across categories of these
you know across different halakhic areas of the category of fruit it
is fascinating within that note that the גמרא Gemara is very willing
to distinguish between types of trees this tree at this stage this
tree at that stage the vine is this so within the sort
of the facts of development I mean the you know Michael says
why is it different for different things I can't tell you because
I don't live with these you know trees every single day but
you know but I mean there's whole books written about agriculture in
the rabbinic times and so on that talk that you know talk
about there really are these differences that you can note and so
it's quite possible to say that you know if you look at
corn and you look at grape and you look at barley and
you look at these fruit and those fruit you'll see at each
stage there's a slightly different stage of development that's meaningful so they're
totally okay to distinguish of the facts of the case within a
category but they assume once you have this abstract conceptual category unripe
fruit is it fruit or not whatever the answer to that is
going to be it's going to be across all these categories right
and this and it makes it easier but it's still a it's
still fascinating that is the assumption so therefore we can bring in
all this evidence from ערלה orla and שמיטה shmita and טומאה tuma
all these things and assume whatever definition it's going to be across
the board and the גמרא Gemara has been has not questioned that
once let's just see the answer now so we still want to
understand why is this כפריסין kafrisin okay for ערלה orla why is
it not a protector of the fruit אלא אמר רבא ela amar
Rava היכא דכי שקלת ליה לשומר מיית פירא heicha deki shaklas lei
leshomer mayis pira when do we say it's a protector of the
fruit for ערלה orla purposes היכא דכי שקלת ליה לשומר מיית פירא
heicha deki shaklas lei leshomer mayis pira if you remove the protector
the fruit will die okay הכא כי שקלת ליה לא מיית פירא
hacha ki shaklas lei lo mayis pira here if you remove the
protector it won't die if you remove this כפריסין kafrisin again whatever
it is berry or a shell does sound more like a shell
anyway so the גמרא Gemara says here's fascinating thing because normally the
גמרא Gemara you know how much does the גמרא Gemara always look
at empirical evidence as a question so look at the next line
הוה עובדא ושקלוה לנץ דרימונא ויבש רימונא hava uvda veshakluha lenetz derimona
veyavesh rimona
so actually they removed the נץ netz of the רימונא rimona which
we said is considered a protector and the pomegranate died ושקלוה לפרחה
דביטסא וחיה ביטסא veshakluha lepircha devitisa vechaya bitisa and they removed the
פרחא pircha of the ביטסא bitisa which is apparently the Aramaic words
of exactly what we're talking about the כפריסין kafrisin of this caper
bush berry and וחיה ביטסא vechaya bitisa
and it didn't die so therefore you see our assertion actually worked
out to be correct and that's why it's not considered a שומר
shomer so we have resolved our problem why by an ערלה orla
bush by a caper bush that's ערלה orla you can throw out
the fruit and eat these כפריסין kafrisin because number one it's not
considered fruit at least when we rely on that position for ערלה
orla maybe by ברכות brachos it is but by כפריסין kafrisin it's
not considered fruit by ערלה orla we will rely on the position
of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that it's not why is it not
a שומר shomer because it's not necessary for the fruit to live
okay and now we've understood why you can do this by the
ערלה orla now what is the upshot of this so if you
notice we have this whole thing here in parentheses and here's what
it says. Let's read in parentheses and then I'll comment about it.
והלכתא *Vehilchasa* the הלכה halacha *Halacha* is כמר בר רב Rav אשי
*keMar Bar Rav Ashi* we rule like מר בר רב Rav אשי
*Mar Bar Rav Ashi* דזרק את האביונות ואכל את הקפריסין *dezarak et
ha'evyonos ve'achal et hakaphrisin*. He threw out the אביונות *evyonos* he ate
the קפריסין *kaphreisin* so it means in חוץ לארץ *Chutz La'aretz* we
don't we only we can consider just the fruit to be the
fruit for ערלה orlah *Orlah* we don't have to worry about the
קפריסין *kaphreisin* by ערלה orlah. *Orlah* and then it says ומדלגבי ערלה
orlah, לא lo, פירא נינהו *umidlegabei Orlah la peira ninhu* and since
we're not considering it a fruit for ערלה orlah, *Orlah* לגבי ברכות
brachos נמי לא lo, פירא נינהו *legabei Brachos nami la peira ninhu*
we won't meaning the קפריסין *kaphreisin* we won't consider קפריסין *kaphreisin* a
fruit for ברכות brachos. *Brachos* which has been our assumption ולא מברכינן
עליה בורא פרי העץ Borei pri ha-eitz. אלא בורא פרי האדמה borei
pri ha-adamah, *vela mivarchinan alei Borei Pri Ha'etz ela Borei Pri Ha'adamah*
we don't say בורא פרי העץ Borei pri ha-eitz. *Borei Pri Ha'etz*
we only say בורא פרי האדמה borei pri ha-adamah *Borei Pri Ha'adamah*.
Okay so basically it concludes that the אביונות *evyonos* we're going to
take a consistent position and it's not going to be considered a
fruit. תוספות Tosafot. *Tosafot* basically says implicitly that this is a גאוניק
*Gaonic* insertion actually there's a couple of והלכתא *Vehilchasa* in this פרק
perek. ברכות brachos. *perek Brachos* that רש"י Rashi *Rashi* explicitly says לא
גרסינן *lo garsinan* and רש"י Rashi *Rashi* and in one place רש"י
Rashi, *Rashi* says לא גרסינן מהלכות גדולות *lo garsinan mihilchos gedolos* that
it was it was glossed over from הלכות גדולות *Hilchos Gedolos* and
I've mentioned this to you a lot of והלכתא *Vehilchasa* מש"ס *mishas*
which is basically saying here's the bottom line הלכה halacha *Halacha* were
not original in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* itself. We're in the הלכות
גדולות *Hilchos Gedolos* which was an early גאוניק *Gaonic* work but that
work quotes the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* and then adds its own line
והלכתא *Vehilchasa* and since that is in ארמית *Aramaic* and he added
it right after the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* it some in very often
got naturally transferred and inserted into the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* itself although
if you notice by this line we just read the grammar is
a little different. It doesn't sound exactly תלמודיק *Talmudic* in some of
in some of the in some of the grammar there. But nevertheless
that's an insertion from הלכות גדולות *Hilchos Gedolos* but then תוספות Tosafot
*Tosafot* goes further and תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says we don't rule that
way. Since קפריסין *kaphreisin* are just it's only a leniency in חוץ
לארץ *Chutz La'aretz* so קפריסין *kaphreisin* really do deserve to be considered
a fruit. Therefore we do say בורא פרי העץ borei pri ha-eitz,
*Borei Pri Ha'etz* by the קפריסין *kaphreisin* even if we're going to
be lenient by ערלה *Orlah* outside of Israel we do say בורא
פרי העץ Borei pri ha-eitz. *Borei Pri Ha'etz* by the קפריסין *kaphreisin*.
Charlie yes.
Where was the הלכות גדולות *Hilchos Gedolos* written?
It was רב Rav יהודאי גאון *Rav Yehudai Gaon* is generally assumed
to be the author of it. There was very different texts of
it in ספרד *Sepharad* and אשכנז *Ashkenaz* and I think in בבל
*Bavel*? Yes Bavel from Baghdad.
That was רב יהודאי
גאון
*Rav Yehudai Gaon*.
Right. Yeah. Okay. Okay.
But the הלכות *Hilchos* are earlier than the רי"ף *Rif* in other
words you're saying גאוניק *Gaonic*?
Yeah yeah. רב יהודאי גאון *Rav Yehudai Gaon* 6th 7th century. רי"ף
*Rif* is let's say 11th century. 10th 11th century whatever. Okay. So
alright so that's the end of that discussion about the caper bush
story. Now גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues. פלפלי *Pilpeli* peppers.
Okay what's the story about peppers? What ברכה bracha, *Bracha* do you
make? So רב ששת אמר *Rav Sheshet amar* שהכל shehakol *shehakol* you
make שהכל shehakol, *shehakol*. רבא Rava אמר *Rava amar* לא כלום *lo
klum* you don't make anything. לאסדא *l'asda* right now the question is
what type of peppers are we talking about now when we have
pepper that we have like what as the spice that's peppercorn right?
Is that at all related to the peppers that we actually have
like red peppers yellow peppers?
Completely unrelated and those are from the new world they would never
have seen them.
Okay. Fine. So but they did have something called dried peppers which
I assume might be like... probably. Yeah would that be like the
hot peppers which are dried and used as spices no those are
all sweet peppers?
These would be the peppercorns from India.
Dried peppers?
The
red peppers are from the new world. Yeah. The only thing they
would call peppers here are what we have ground up into black
pepper and white pepper.
Oh so they they did have the what we call peppercorns. Alright
I misunderstood you. Okay. Okay from the new world?
No no. The the little chili peppers are from there. Okay. Those
they would never have.
Okay fine. So we're talking about the stuff that could be dried
and made into peppercorn right?
Well it comes it basically is harvested dried. Yeah.
Okay it's harvested dried so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is about to
introduce a difference between whether it's moist or whether it's dried.
In in those times it may have been... Okay.
So anyway so we're talking about basically we're talking about the type
of pepper that we call now pepper that you know black pepper.
Okay. רב ששת אמר *Rav Sheshet amar* שהכל shehakol. *shehakol* you make
שהכל shehakol *shehakol* so there's a question what do you make on
spices which are not normally eaten straight. רבא Rava אמר *Rava amar*
לא כלום *lo klum* you don't make anything. ולאסדא *vela'asda* because you
don't eat it
straight. ורבא לטעמיה *veRava leta'ameih* Rava goes according to his reasoning דאמר
רבא Rava *de'amar Rava* כס פלפלי *kas pilpeli* if somebody chews pepper
ביום הכיפורים *beYom Hakippurim* פטור patur, *patur* you're exempt it's not considered
food you haven't eaten. כס זנגבילא *kas zangvila* if you chew ginger
ביום הכיפורים *beYom Hakippurim* פטור *patur* you're exempt. Okay because that's not
food it's a spice it's not food.
אבל אסור *aval assur* it's forbidden.
Does that change
because like people now eat ginger?
Well let's see. מיתיבי *meitivei* I'll ask you on this. היה רבי
מאיר אומר *haya Rabbi Meir omer* ממשמע שנאמר *mimashma shene'emar* back to
ערלה *Orlah* so now we've introduced by the way again notice how
we're cross-categorizing what's a food by ברכות *Brachos* food by יום כיפור
*Yom Kippur* now we're back to ערלה *Orlah*. Since it says by
ערלה *Orlah* וערלתם ערלתו את פריו *va'araltem orlato et piryo* you should
make off limits the fruit. איני יודע שעץ מאכל ma’achal הוא *eini
yodea she'etz ma'achal hu* don't I know that it's a a tree
that produces fruit? אלא מה תלמוד לומר עץ מאכל *ela mah talmud
lomar etz ma'achal*?
Okay because that's the phrase used in the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* עץ
מאכל *etz ma'achal* a a fruit-bearing fruit tree. So why did it
have to say that? Obviously it's fruit. To tell you that it
includes the fruit the tree that it tastes like the fruit. What
is that? גמרא Gemara other places say it's an אתרוג, etrog, but
that's not what it says
here. ואיזהו זה, ואיזהו זה הפלפלין. Ve-eizehu zeh, ve-eizehu zeh ha-pilpilin. That
is peppers. Apparently it says that the bark of a pepper... what
do you get a peppercorn from? A bush or tree, Charlie? I'm
looking it up right now. Okay. So wherever you get a peppercorn
from, apparently the bark or the tree itself tastes similar to the
actual
spice. ללמדך שהפלפלין חייבין בערלה. Lelamedcha she-ha-pilpilin chayavin be-orlah. The purpose is
to tell you that you're חייב chayav in ערלה even by peppercorn.
וללמדך שאין ארץ ישראל חסרה כלום, U-lelamedcha she-ein Eretz Yisrael chasera klum,
that everything is in Israel, even pepper bushes or trees or whatever
they are. וכשנאמר, U-ke-shenemar, the פסוק says, ארץ אשר לא במסכנות תאכל
בה לחם לא תחסר כל בה, Eretz asher lo ve-miskenut tochal bah
lechem lo techsar kol bah, you will not eat bread in poverty,
nothing will be lacking from it, except for oil. So right. So
anyway, so what do we learn from this? That peppers are חייב
chayav in ערלה. And again we're back to our קשיא. kashya. If
peppers are חייב chayav in ערלה, they must be a fruit. If
they're a fruit, היי דשמיטה דאורייתא, hai dishmitah de-Oraisa, certainly you should
not say no ברכה, bracha. maybe you should even say בורא פרי
העץ. Borei pri ha-eitz. Now maybe it's a fruit that's not normally
eaten, whatever, but at least you shouldn't say no ברכה. bracha. So
let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. לא קשיא הא ברטיבתא והא
ביבשתא. Lo kashya ha bir-tivta ve-ha bir-yaveshta.
It depends whether they're moist or dried out. We are talking when
they're dried out and turn into a type of a spice; then
it's not normal food, then according to רבא Rava you don't make
a ברכה. bracha When it's moist, that's maybe an open question. Who
knows? Maybe even make a בורא פרי העץ. borei pri haetz Okay,
so take a look at תוספות. Tosafot. So תוספות Tosafot says, כגון
ליטואריו, kegon lituaryo, I have no idea what that is, בלע"ז מברכין
עליה בורא פרי האדמה. be-la'az mevorachin aleha borei pri ha-adamah. So he
says you don't say בורא פרי העץ, borei pri haetz you say
בורא פרי האדמה, which is interesting. אבל יבשתא לא מברכין לה. Aval
yaveshta lo mevorachin lah.
Now he might be talking not about the pepper; he might be
talking about some other type of a spice. וכן הלכה בזנגבילא, Ve-chen
halacha be-zangvila,
which is our ginger, בלע"ז be-la'az and so on. וכל דבר שדרכו
לאוכלו ברטיבא, Ve-chol davar she-darko le-ochlo bir-tiva, things that are only eaten
when they're moist, אין
מברכין להו כלל ביבשתא. ein mevorachin lehu klal be-yaveshta. You don't make
any ברכה bracha when they're dry. So things that are only eaten
directly when they're moist, when they're dried they're treated as a spice,
you don't make a ברכה bracha directly if you eat them.
If I go to the
store, one minute, אבל עץ שפינמון, aval eitz she-pinamon, how about cinnamon
sticks, שקורין קנילא, she-korin kanila, מברכין עליה בורא פרי האדמה. mevorachin aleha
borei pri ha-adamah. That you do make a ברכה bracha even dried.
ומשום דאורחיה למיכל הכי, U-mishum de-orchei le-michal hachi, people eat dried cinnamon
sticks. וכמה גולה ארץ, Ve-chama golah eretz, and then he talks about
eating sugarcane, וחץ סוכר, ve-chatz sukkar, sugarcane,
מברכין בורא פרי העץ, mevarchin borei pri ha-eitz, because sugarcane is a
type of a tree, he says. So תוספות Tosafot says it all
has to do with whether we eat it. If we eat it
dried, you make a ברכה bracha. and the natural ברכה. bracha If
you only eat it moist and dried it's only a spice and
you never eat it directly, and only use it to spice food,
then you don't make a ברכה bracha when you eat it directly.
So presumably, if you would eat this peppercorn moist, since we see
it's ערלה, presumably you would make בורא פרי העץ. borei pri haetz.
What do you see there, Charlie? Where do we get peppercorn from?
It is from a woody
vine. A vine.
Well, okay, and is it a vine that lasts from year to
year? Yes. Oh, so there you go, so it would then be
like grapes, so we'd make בורא פרי העץ.
But does that change these days? I mean, people eat ginger.
Yes, so what people normally eat dried will change and you see
that from תוספות. Tosfos. תוספות Tosfos. is all talking about what do
we do nowadays. So nowadays you don't have to
go like תוספות Tosfos because depending on case-by-case. Right. I mean for
instance with ginger, people eat... you go to the store, you buy
dried ginger.
You buy dried ginger to eat directly or to use
to... really?
Okay.
Yeah, it's got sugar on it, it's good.
Okay, I didn't know that. All right, מונח. munach.
Yeah, you buy it
for a snack at Costco. All right. So now the גמרא Gemara
continues. Okay. אמרו ליה רבנן למימר. Amru leh rabanan le-Meimar. So the
rabbis, meaning the rabbinic students,
said to Meimar, כסס זנגבילא ביומא דכיפורי פטור. Kassas zangvila be-yoma de-kippuri
patur. If you chew ginger on Yom Kippur you're פטור, which was
the other thing רבא said. ואמר רבא, Va-amar Rava, doesn't רבא himself
say, some say רבינא Ravina says, so it's not רבא himself, האי
המלתא דאתי מהנדוא, hai hamalta de-asi mi-Hindua, this ginger that comes from
India, שריא, sharya, is permissible, ומברכינן עליה בורא פרי האדמה, u-mevarchinan alei
borei pri ha-adamah, and we make בורא פרי האדמה
on it. So here you see that he considered ginger to be
a food that you would make a ברכה bracha on. So the
גמרא Gemara. says, לא קשיא, lo kashya, it's not difficult, הא ברטיבתא
והא ביבשתא, ha bir-tivta ve-ha bir-yaveshta, same answer: moist or dried. Moist
ginger apparently they would make a ברכה bracha on, they would eat;
dried ginger they would not and that's the difference. Okay, ginger grows
how? What is ginger? Like a root. It's a root. Okay, all
right. Yeah, I saw that.
No, the root is what we eat.
Fine. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says, okay. חביץ קדירה, Chavitz
kdera,
now how about this חביץ קדירה, chavitz kdera, which is basically some
type of a mixture of
oil... it's like a sweet oatmeal type of a thing, you've got
honey and oil and flour. What ברכה bracha do you make on
it?
Doesn't it sound like that fish thing?
No, no fish. Okay. וכן דייסא, ve-chen daysa, which we... דייסא daysa
is the current Israeli word for oatmeal, but actually it seems here
that it was not even cooked, it might have just been like
a type of a crushed grainy that they ate. But these seem
like processed food. Okay, yeah, maybe something like granola. What ברכה beracha
would you make on רב יהודה אמר Rav Yehuda amar שהכל נהיה
בדברו, shehakol nihiya bidvaro, you make שהכל shehakol because people don't normally
eat it in this state. רב כהנא אמר Rav Kahana amar בורא
מיני מזונות, borei minei mezonos, you make a בורא מיני מזונות. borei
minei mezonos. So notice by the way there are three possibilities. Well
okay, meaning you can make like a בורא פרי העץ on
something. Let's not get to מזונות mezonos yet, let me just take
a second to reflect back on the ginger and pepper discussion. Okay,
there was a question why you make no ברכה beracha, or שהכל,
shehakol, but nobody said you make a בורא פרי העץ by the
dried pepper. So everybody agrees that once it's not in the state
in which it's normally eaten, you don't make the classic ברכה, beracha
you don't make the בורא פרי העץ. The question becomes is it
so crazy to eat it that you make no ברכה beracha or
is
it at least, you know, a reasonable number of people do it,
it's not so crazy and then you at least you would make
a שהכל. shehakol, So that was the issue around the pepper, about
the dried pepper. But it's important to note that a ברכה beracha
could be demoted two ways. It could be demoted to שהכל shehakol.
if it's the not normal way to eat
it, but still a certain some times it's eaten this way and
it can be demoted to nothing if it's crazy that it's not
even considered food. Now we're talking about a different question if you
would not about demoted but promoted. What type at what stage maybe
does something become a בורא מיני מזונות? borei minei mezonos? So first
of all if it's totally raw it does not become בורא מיני
מזונות. borei minei mezonos. It has to be cooked or baked. Okay?
So let's take a look now at presumably this stuff here is
cooked. Okay? So then it should be a בורא מיני מזונות. borei
minei mezonos. So let's see what the issue is.
That's to say boiled. It doesn't have to be מעשה תנור. maaseh
tanur.
Right right right. Boiled, right, boiled. Like oatmeal on the stove. Right,
exactly. I mean even rice which isn't a real grain as we're
about to find, you still make מזונות mezonos even though you just
cook it. Right? It doesn't have to be baked or whatever, it
basically has to be cooked, boiled, or whatever to be מזונות. mezonos.
But presumably that was done here one minute, so let's see what
the issue is. So רבינא Ravina so one opinion is שהכל shehakol?
and רב כהנא Rav Kahana says בורא מיני מזונות. borei minei mezonos.
דייסא גרידא, daisa greida, if we're talking about straight crushed grain boiled
presumably like a type of an oatmeal, כולי עלמא לא פליגי דבורא
מיני מזונות. kulei alma lo pligi de-borei minei mezonos. Of course you
make בורא מיני מזונות, borei minei mezonos, straight oatmeal. כי פליגי בדייסא
כעין חביץ קדירה. ki pligi bedaisa ke-ein chavitz kedeira. We're talking about
a type of an oatmeal that you made like a חביץ קדירה,
chavitz kedeira, meaning some people can't eat plain oatmeal, they pour tons
of sugar and maple syrup. So you put a ton of maple
syrup into your oatmeal. So what ברכה beracha do you make? So
רב יהודה אמר Rav Yehuda amar שהכל, she-hakol. you make שהכל, shehakol,
סבר דובשא עיקר. savar dusha ikar. You're really interested in the honey,
in the maple syrup. Sounds like sometimes how my kids eat their
cereal, right? Why don't you have some oatmeal with your maple syrup?
רב כהנא אמר Rav Kahana amar בורא מיני מזונות, borei minei mezonos,
no you make מזונות, mezonos, סבר סמידא עיקר. savar smida ikar.
The flour is what is עיקר. ikar. Okay, so אמר רב יוסף
כוותיה דרב כהנא מסתברא. amar Rav Yosef kevasei de-Rav Kahana mistabra. Makes
sense like רב כהנא. Rav Kahana. דרב ושמואל דאמרי תרוייהו de-Rav u-Shmuel
de-amri tarvaihu because רב and שמואל Shmuel both say... Now of course
what's the question of what's עיקר? ikar? Is this for us to
decide objectively? Is this based on the person? Does this change from
society to society? Right? How what factors do you use to determine
this? So let's see how the גמרא Gemara concludes. We're going to
say that it is that it's בורא מיני מזונות borei minei mezonos
because רב and שמואל Shmuel both say כל שיש בו מחמשת המינים
מברכין עליו בורא מיני מזונות. kol she-yesh bo michameshes haminim mevarachin alav
borei minei mezonos. Anything that contains the חמשת המינים, chameshes haminim, the
five grains, right? Wheat, barley, spelt, oats, and rye, we make בורא
מיני מזונות. borei minei mezonos. Which means that it doesn't really matter
what you think. At least in this case. We have in this
case we have a הלכה halacha definition that overrides. We're always going
to say that מזונות mezonos is עיקר. ikar. Now I want to
point this out because this will be an ongoing theme that it's
not so clear from the משנה. mishnah. משנה mishnah we're going to
see later speaks about eating herring with some bread to sop up
the saltiness and says you don't make a ברכה beracha on the
bread because the herring is עיקר ikar and the bread is the
טפל. tafel. Okay? But the גמרא Gemara? somewhat reverses that and the
גמרא Gemara, basically says whenever there's bread in the room it's המוציא.
Hamotzi. Whenever there's מזונות mezonos in the room it's בורא מיני מזונות
borei minei mezonos in the mixture, that's always defined as עיקר. ikar.
The one exception the גמרא Gemara has is when the מזונות mezonos
is only come לדבוקי בעלמא, lidvukei be-alma, coming to sort of like,
you know, to stick the stuff together. But if it is there
to provide some sustenance and to fill you, the מזונות mezonos objectively,
bread objectively is the meal, right? That is defined as the meal.
Bread is the staff of life. מזונות mezonos always objectively is the
עיקר. ikar. So you understand the logic but it is worth pointing
out that's not necessarily the position of... doesn't seem to be the
פשט pshat of the משניות. mishnayos. So here the גמרא Gemara saying
is that the מזונות mezonos takes wins and therefore because the even
if you're interested presumably in the honey you make a בורא מיני
מזונות. borei minei mezonos. Okay? So let's take a look. By the
way, the example I gave you the other day about sushi you
wouldn't say it because there it's rice. Even though you make a
rice מזונות mezonos on rice it's not חמשת המינים. chameshes haminim. This
is specifically about the five types of grain.
So sushi is שהכל.
shehakol What? So sushi is שהכל? shehakol Well it depends which one
is עיקר ikar for you. Okay. Maybe today I'm interested in this,
yesterday I was interested in that. Okay, so it depends there it's
more possible subjective. But when it's the חמשת המינים chameshes haminim and
it's not just coming לדבוקי, lidvukei, the הלכה becomes that becomes the
objective. You want to make a ברכה bracha on both. Of course
the question is, yeah, okay, that's a way to get out of
it if there is no עיקר ikar and טפל. tafel. Now the
question I'm getting a little ahead of myself but I should say...
The always interesting question is like what do you call it like
when you do
bread crumb covered like שניצל. schnitzel. So it's not
לדבוקי, le-dvukei, but give me a break, it's very clear what's עיקר
ikar what's טפל tafel there. I don't know anybody who says you
make a בורא מיני מזונות borei minei mezonos on שניצל. schnitzel. So
there is a question about what would be in a similar category
of לדבוקי le-dvukei that it's not really there to fill you, it's
just doing some type of a culinary function, you know. But that
is the basic position by the grains. Let's just look at תוספות.
Tosfos כל שיש בו מחמשת המינים מברכין בורא מיני מזונות, kol she-yesh
bo mi-chameshet ha-minim me-varchin borei minei mezonos, says תוספות. Tosfos וכן קליטריש
בלע"ז שעושין מקמח ומים או מחלב מברכין בורא מיני מזונות. ve-chen klitris
be-la’az she-osin mi-kemach u-mayim o mei-chalav me-varchin borei minei mezonos. וכן שנותנים
קמח לתוך פולין ve-chen she-notnin kemach l’toch pulin
when you add flour into פולין pulin which is what, some type
of a legume, או לתוך עדשים o l’toch adashim beans, או כרישים,
o krishim, וכן לתוך שקדים שעושין לחולה, ve-chen l’toch shkedim she-osin la-chole,
apparently they would add do some things with nuts and flour. אם
עושה אותו כדי לסעוד הלב, im ose oto k’dei lis’od ha-lev,
if the flour is added in order to fill you, then אז
צריך לברך בורא מיני מזונות. az tzarich l’varech borei minei mezonos. ואם
לדבק בעלמא ve-im l’davek b’alma if it's just sort of doing to
stick the stuff together, אין צריך. ein tzarich. And now comes תוספות
Tosfos which comes how a lot of people's general attitude to all
these ברכות cases like Michael said, וטוב להחמיר ולגומו בתוך הסעודה לאחר
ברכת המוציא פוטר מכולם נפשך. ve-tov l’hachmir u-l’gomo b’toch ha-seuda l’acher birkat
ha-motzi poter mi-kulam nafsh’cha. תוספות Tosfos says
if you have any doubt, just do it when you're always eating
bread. Or what other people do, I'll have a little bit of
a cookie and I'll make a מזונות mezonos on that and then
I'll have a little bit of a carrot and I'll make an
אדמה adama on that and then I can יצא yeitzei whatever ברכה
bracha I have to make here. So this idea of טוב להחמיר
tov l’hachmir and doing it during a meal comes up in תוספות
Tosfos's after תוספות Tosafos in this פרק. Okay, which is an interesting
sort of whole attitude although he's pretty clear what the פסק psak
is, he says play safe. Okay, but the point also is תוספות
Tosafos gives you two extremes, doing to fill you up and doing
לדבוקי. le-dvukei. There are things that are not there to fill you
up and they're also not there לדבוקי. le-dvukei. Like I said, you
add it to be a crunch. That would be another example. You
have what's called like apple crunch or whatever that basically you just
add like crunchy stuff on the top and it's probably there for
taste purposes, not for filling purposes, right? It's for the crunch purpose.
Is that לדבוקי le-dvukei or is it לסעוד? lis’od? Do you make
a מזונות mezonos on that or do you not?
Yeah, but what I was saying before is yes, that's one way.
But someone suggested לכתחילה le-chatchila make the
ברכה bracha.
on both? No, because it's treated as one object that gets one
ברכה. bracha Unless you say there is an interesting question, let's say
there's no עיקר וטפל. ikar ve-tafel. Let's say you have
a type of a salad that is like cut up melons together
with cut up cherries. Okay, and they're both of equal importance to
you. It's not like one is עיקר ikar and one is טפל.
tafel. So that's an interesting question. There maybe you do have to
make both ברכות. Okay, but normally as the הלכה goes, it's one
מאכל and you make the ברכה bracha on the עיקר. ikar. Anyway,
גופא, gufa, so let's take a look now
at the גמרא. Gemara Now we get into this idea of מזונות.
mezonos. גופא, gufa, let's take a look at that source. רב ושמואל
דאמרי תרווייהו, Rav u-Shmuel d’amri tarvaihu, רב ושמואל Rav u-Shmuel both said,
כל שיש בו מחמשת המינים מברכים עליו בורא מיני מזונות. kol she-yesh
bo mi-chameshet ha-minim me-varchim alav borei minei mezonos. ואיתמר נמי v’itmar nami
it's also said, רב ושמואל דאמרי תרווייהו, Rav u-Shmuel d’amri tarvaihu, רב
ושמואל Rav u-Shmuel both said, כל שהוא מחמשת המינים מברכים בורא מיני
מזונות. kol she-hu mi-chameshet ha-minim me-varchim borei minei mezonos. The first one
is any mixture as long as it has the five grains is
מזונות. mezonos. Here it's saying any product you make out of the
five grains, cookies, wafers, any product gets a בורא מיני מזונות. borei
minei mezonos. Except for bread. וצריכי, ve-tzrichi, you need to say both.
Oatmeal? דאי אשמעינן כל שהוא, de-ei ashma’inan kol she-hu, anything made of
the five grains, not a mixture, הוה אמינא משום דאיתא בעיניה, hava
amina mishum d’ita b’einei, you only say מזונות mezonos because it's the
only thing, it's just the grains. אבל על ידי תערובת, aval al
yedei ta’arovet, if it's in a mixture, לא, maybe you would not
make מזונות, mezonos, maybe you would make like on the honey, you'd
make a שהכל. shehakol קא משמע לן, ka mashma lan, top of
ל"ז, lamed zayin, so this teaches us כל שיש בו kol she-yesh
bo that even if it's just a, even if it's just one
of the ingredients, it's still מזונות. mezonos. ואי אשמעינן כל שיש בו
ve-ei ashma’inan kol she-yesh bo so just tell me that as long
as it's an ingredient you make בורא מיני מזונות, borei minei mezonos,
הוה אמינא כל שיש בו חמשת המינים אין, hava amina kol she-yesh
bo chameshet ha-minim in,
that's where when we say it's an ingredient then you make a
מזונות, mezonos, that's when it's the five
grains. אבל אורז ודוחן, aval orez v’dochan, אורז orez and דוחן, dochan,
which I will translate as תוספות's Tosafos translation is rice and milk?
Millet. Rice and millet, I don't know, Steinsaltz gives you the picture,
he tells you what the classification is. רש"י Rashi says that אורז
orez is millet and דוחן dochan he says is something else, פנץ,
pantz, I wasn't able to find out what the פנץ pantz in
רש"י meant. Normally they're interpreted to be rice and millet. Okay, but
when it comes to rice and millet, לא, then you don't make
a מזונות. mezonos. Why? משום דעל ידי תערובת mishum d’al yedei ta’arovet
because it's in a mixture. אבל איתא בעיניה, aval ita b’einei, I
would have assumed that if you have something made straight out of
rice or you're eating straight
rice, נימא, neima, you should say בורא מיני מזונות. borei minei mezonos.
אפילו אורז ודוחן נמי מברכין, afilu orez v’dochan nami me-varchin, I would
have said, אפילו אורז ודוחן נמי מברכין עליו בורא מיני מזונות, afilu
orez v’dochan nami me-varchin alav borei minei mezonos, you make מזונות mezonos
even on rice and millet. קא משמע לן, ka mashma lan, so
therefore רב ושמואל Rav u-Shmuel teaches us no, כל שהוא מחמשת המינים,
kol she-hu mi-chameshet ha-minim, even if it's coming by itself you only
make בורא מיני מזונות borei minei mezonos if it's of the five
grains. לא מברכינן עליה בורא מיני מזונות, lo mevarchenan alei borei minei
mezonos, לאפוקי אורז ודוחן la-apukei orez vedochan as opposed to rice and
millet, דאפילו איתא בעיניה dafilu isa be-enei even when it's by itself,
לא מברכינן עליה בורא מיני מזונות. lo mevarchenan alei borei minei mezonos.
You do not make בורא מיני מזונות. borei minei mezonos. Everybody here
knows we make מזונות mezonos on rice, but we are going to
see now that the גמרא Gemara is figuring that out and it's
not and it's not a consensus. So רב and שמואל Shmuel are
saying rice and millet count for nothing, they're אדמה adama all the
time, the only thing that's מזונות mezonos are the five grains. So
when they are coming by themselves, when they're mixed, they will always
be מזונות mezonos even if it's an ingredient. But rice and millet
and anything not the five grains you will never make a בורא
מיני מזונות. borei minei mezonos. So now let's see where the גמרא
Gemara goes.
What about לאפוקי la-apukei or not לאפוקי la-apukei that the גמרא? Gemara
The לאפוקי la-apukei criteria
is not yet in the גמרא, Gemara that comes up later. That
which תוספות Tosafos refer to over
here. Right. Correct. And I was incorporating it later. The גמרא has
not yet introduced that category. Okay. So now, fine. So now the
גמרא says like this: ואורז ודוחן לא מברכינן בורא מיני מזונות? ve'orez
vedochan lo mevarchenan borei minei mezonos? You mean to tell me you
don't make מזונות mezonos on rice and millet? והתניא, vehatanya, don't we
teach in a ברייתא: Baraisa: היו לפניו פת אורז ופת דוחן, hayu
lefanav pas orez upas dochan, if they brought in front of somebody
rice bread or millet bread, מברך עליו תחילה וסוף כמעשה קדירה, mevarech
alav techila vesof kemayseh kederah,
you make the ברכה bracha at the beginning and the end like
you make by various types of... מעשה קדירה mayseh kederah refers to
things made in a pot using flour. Okay, so various things used
sort of that you make, various different types of flour products, not
bread. Okay, things that are cooked, cooked flour products are מעשה קדירה.
mayseh kederah. So וגבי מעשה קדירה תניא, vegabi mayseh kederah tanya, by
מעשה קדירה mayseh kederah we teach: בתחילה מברך עליו בורא מיני מזונות,
betchila mevarech alav borei minei mezonos, you make a בורא מיני מזונות
borei minei mezonos in the beginning, ובסוף מברך עליו ברכה אחת מעין
שלש, uvasof mevarech alav bracha achas me'ein shalosh, and at the end
you make the one ברכה bracha which is like three, which is
the על המחיה. Al Hamichya.
So cholent is not מעשה קדירה? mayseh kederah?
No, no, no. מעשה קדירה mayseh kederah is not just anything you
make in a pot. מעשה קדירה mayseh kederah specifically is like, is
like flour products made in a pot. Okay. So so the גמרא
says like this: where are we? Right, if you look at רש"י,
what he says, מעשה קדירה של חמשת מינין. mayseh kederah shel chameshas
minim. Okay, the last the third line from of רש"י from the
top. Okay, so now the גמרא says: כמעשה קדירה ולא כמעשה קדירה.
kemayseh kederah velo kemayseh kederah.
Yeah. Like מעשה קדירה mayseh kederah but not exactly the same. כמעשה
קדירה, kemayseh kederah, like מעשה קדירה mayseh kederah דמברך עליו תחילה וסוף,
demevarech alav techila vesof, you make a ברכה bracha beginning and end.
ולא כמעשה קדירה, velo kemayseh kederah, but not the same ברכות. דאילו
במעשה קדירה בתחילה בורא מיני מזונות ובסוף ברכה אחת מעין שלש, de'ilu
bemayseh kederah betchila borei minei mezonos uvasof bracha achas me'ein shalosh, by
these types of flour products you make מזונות mezonos and על המחיה.
Al Hamichya. ואילו הכא בתחילה מברך עליו שהכל נהיה בדברו, ve'ilu hacha
betchila mevarech alav shehakol nihiyeh bidvaro, by rice you say שהכל, ובסוף
בורא נפשות רבות וחסרונן על כל מה שברא. uvasof borei nefashos rabos
vechesronan al kol mah shebara. Okay, so which is which is like
crazy, because why do you say oh it's just like, you know,
it's just like a dough products? What do you mean you're just
like? Oh, you make a ברכה bracha beginning and end. What don't
you make a ברכה bracha at beginning and end? So, but this
is how the גמרא gets out of it. Clearly this ברייתא Baraisa
seems to treat rice and millet as a classic מזונות mezonos for
בורא מיני מזונות borei minei mezonos and for על המחיה, Al Hamichya,
but the גמרא gets out of it and says no, no, no,
the comparison really doesn't mean anything and you really just make a
שהכל and בורא נפשות. borei nefashos. So we have these two extremes
by rice. One is total type of a שהכל בורא נפשות. borei
nefashos. It's actually interesting that it says שהכל and not אדמה. adama.
Yeah. I don't know exactly anyway. So one is that possibility, and
the other is that real extreme, the other extreme is it's totally
מזונות. mezonos. We're going to see the גמרא is eventually going to
conclude our position, which is you make a בורא מזונות borei mezonos
at the end and you and a בורא נפשות borei nefashos at
the beginning, which is the I mean, you reverse that. בורא מזונות
borei mezonos at the beginning and a בורא נפשות borei nefashos at
the end, which is a very bizarre marriage, a combination, and we
will see that. Before we end today's אור, ohr, I just want
to say about this ברכה bracha, בורא נפשות רבות, borei nefashos rabos,
it's the first we're being introduced with it. So תוספות here explains,
I won't read the תוספות for time, but he says the language
is the following: בורא נפשות רבות וחסרונן, borei nefashos rabos vechesronan, you
create for people everything that they need. So חסרונן chesronan things that
we really need, that that would include like salt, water, things that
are necessary for life. על כל מה שבראת להחיות בהם נפש כל
חי. al kol mah shebarasa lehachayos bahem nefesh kol chai. And not
only things that we need, you've given us everything that we need
to make life beautiful. So therefore it includes things like, you know,
eggs and milk and and meat and all these other things. So
that becomes an all-inclusive ברכה, bracha but it's interesting that תוספות says
the נוסח nusach emphasizes that it includes both necessities and also things
that are pleasures and not necessities, and all of that is in
the ברכה of בורא נפשות. borei nefashos.